创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning there was darkness,
随着一声爆炸
and then, bang--
诞生了无尽膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在揭秘这个诡异
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
震撼 神秘莫测的
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
地方 - 我们所谓的《宇宙》
of a place we call "The Universe."
要是我们的月球突然消失又当如何呢？
What would happen if our Moon suddenly disappeared?
全球性海啸将摧毁世界各地的海岸线
Global tsunamis decimate coastlines around the world,
因为海水涌向了太阳的引力
as ocean waters surge toward the gravitational pull of the Sun.
洋流变化
Sea currents shift,
改变着气象模式 破坏了食品供应
changing weather patterns and destroying food supplies.
最终地球自转轴倾角失控
Eventually Earth's axis tilts wildly,
变两极为热带丛林
turning the poles into tropical jungles
赤道成寒冷的不毛之地
and the equator into frigid wastelands.
新的物种出现 其它物种则消亡
New species emerge, while others go extinct.
我们的星球变得面目全非
Our planet becomes unrecognizable
月球消失后的日子
the day the Moon was gone.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：HDC字幕组 调校：晴天 招募Q号: 76846146
历史频道 - 宇宙 第4季第2集 月球消失后的日子
The History Channel - The Universe s04e02 The Day The Moon Was Gone
月球是一块荒凉 毫无生机的石头
The Moon is a barren, lifeless rock,
但是它在地球生命的故事里扮演了一个出人意料的重要角色
but it plays a surprisingly important role in the story of life on Earth.
有多重要？
How important?
我们来把它从空中拿走看看
Let's remove it from the sky and find out.
怪事几乎立马就会发生
Strange things start to happen almost immediately.
海边的人们首先会注意到变化
People on the coast are the first to notice the change.
它或许会造成诸如海啸
This would probably create something like a tsunami,
大潮汐 确实是极具戏剧性的
a tidal wave, which would be very dramatic indeed.
众所周知 月球控制着地球的潮涨潮落
It's well known that the Moon controls Earth's tides.
在它围绕着我们运转的过程中其质量把我们的海洋拉向它
As it orbits around us, its mass tugs our oceans toward it,
引起潮汐被拽向了地球最靠近月球的那一面
causing a tidal bulge on the side of the planet nearest the Moon.
由于引力物理学上的怪事
And through a strange quirk of gravitational physics,
它形成了第二个涌起
it forms a second bulge
在远离月球的那一面
on the side farthest away from the Moon.
很少有人知道太阳也在管控潮汐中发挥了作用
Few people realize the Sun also plays a role in governing the tides,
但是因为它距离我们比月球远400倍
but because it's 400 times farther from us than the Moon,
其对海洋的引力作用
its gravitational influence on the oceans
相对较小 约占整个影响的三分之一
is relatively small, about 1/3 of the total effect.
但是随着月球的出局
But with the Moon out of the picture,
现在太阳当上了家
the Sun is now in control.
由于月球高高在上
With the Moon up here,
其引力可以说是把水泡拉起
its gravitational pull is sort of pulling a dome of water up.
有一个大的涌起
There's a big sort of bulge.
来想象一下剪断其联系
Then imagine you just snipped the cord
水就必定会回流
and the water had to flow back out.
水会涌向太阳的引力
The water rushes toward the gravity of the Sun
形成一个巨大的全球性海啸
in a massive global tsunami.
取决于月球的海浪的力量
The force of the waves
在月球消失后就与太阳有关了
depends on where the Moon is in relation to the Sun when it disappears.
如果月球消失在满月即新月时
If the Moon vanished at full moon or at new moon,
也就是月球与地球 太阳连成一线时
that's when the Moon is lined up with the Earth and the Sun.
月球的潮涌
The lunar tidal bulges
就会减弱同一地点的太阳潮涌
would shrink to solar tidal bulges in the same spots,
来自月球潮涌额外的海水
and the extra water from the lunar bulges
会很快流向世界其他地方
would quickly flow to other parts of the globe.
但是存在着更加戏剧的可能性
But there's an even more dramatic possibility.
如果月球消失在弦月时
If the Moon vanished when it's at quarter moon,
不管是上弦月还是下弦月
either first quarter or last quarter,
那时的月球潮涌是不会在同时出现在
then the Moon's tidal bulge is not in the same place
太阳潮涌的地方的
as the Sun's tidal bulge.
因此我预计你会看到地球上的海水
And so I expect you would see a very quick motion of Earth's oceans
会从月球潮涌快速流向太阳潮涌
from the lunar tidal bulge to the solar tidal bulge.
有些专家认为
Some experts believe
这种海水更为剧烈的横向侧移
this more drastic lateral shift in ocean water
会冲击全球沿海各地
would blast coastal spots around the world.
猛烈的冲击将类同于2004年南亚大海啸
The powerful pulses would be similar to the 2004 Southeast Asian tsunami,
除了波涛会造成更大的伤亡和破坏
except the waves would cause even more death and destruction
因为那是世界性的
since they'd be worldwide.
两个巨大的从东到西和从西到东的波浪
Two massive east-to-west and west-to-east waves
将分别在地球的相对的两端发起
would be initiated on opposite ends of the Earth.
迈阿密这样的海滨城市将遭遇50英尺高的水墙
A seaside city like Miami would be pummeled by a 50-foot wall of water
会摧毁大多数沿岸建筑
that would destroy most coastal buildings
横扫整个佛罗里达州南部
and sweep across the entire width of southern Florida,
危及900万生命
putting nine million lives at risk.
然而对于这样一个巨大的海水移动
But with such a titanic shift of water,
还会有什么别的不可预测的后果呢？
could there be other unpredictable results?
可以想象得到 海水的东西向
One can imagine that perhaps the east-west
南北向的运动可能会扰乱洋流
or north-south motion of that water could disrupt the currents.
墨西哥暖流会把温暖的海水从加勒比送往英国
The Gulf Stream carries warm water from the Caribbean up to Great Britain,
帮助维持了英国比它实际位置要暖和很多
and it helps keep Great Britain a lot warmer
想想它其实是很靠北方的
than it otherwise would be, considering how far north it is.
气候是个很微妙的系统
Climate is a very delicate system,
你调整其中一部分 其他部分就会有所反应
and you tweak one part of it and another part responds.
因而可以想见粮食生产
And then one can imagine that food productivity
以及整个生活方式都将发生极大的转变
and the overall way of life would be dramatically altered
要是北欧更加寒冷的话
if it were cooler in northern Europe.
撒哈拉大沙漠就是个很好的例子
The Sahara Desert is a great example of someplace
过去曾经是绿意盎然 而现在则完全是个不毛之地
that used to be green and lush and now is completely a desert.
气候带来的变化
Having changes with climate
确实可以影响到我们的生存
can really have impact on our survival.
不过我们星球上最大的影响
But the biggest impact on our planet
莫过于改变地球倾角的稳定
would be the changes to Earth's steady tilt,
这种独特的特点
a unique feature
给了我们有规律的四季
that gives us our four regular seasons.
我们地球的倾角一直固定在
The thing that locks our planet's tilt
约23 5度的关键就在于
to about 23.5 degrees so consistently
月球的存在充当了巨大的稳定器
is the presence of the Moon that acts as a large stabilizer.
要是我们不再有月球的话
If we don't have the Moon anymore,
我们就可能陷入的状况更多的就像火星
we may get into a regime that's much more like Mars.
火星 并没有稳定的23 5度倾角
And Mars, instead of being at a stable 23.5 degrees,
经受着狂乱的倾角变化
goes through wild variations of the tilt,
呈现出最低从低至15度
varying from maybe as low as 15 degrees on the low side,
一直到最高约75 80度那个样子
all the way up to something like about 75, 80 degrees on the high side.
没有了月球 我们的地轴就会在几十万年里
Without the Moon, our axis begins fluctuating erratically
开始不正常的摆动
over several hundred thousand years.
太阳系里的其他行星的引力
The gravitational pull from other planets in the solar system
会开始肆虐地球
starts wreaking havoc on Earth.
我们正常的季节会随着我们星球在某些时期里
Our stable seasons shift dramatically as different parts of our planet
急剧地倒向太阳而发生戏剧性的变化
tilt radically toward the Sun during some periods
不复存在
and away at others.
你失去月球后不久
Soon as you get rid of the Moon,
就会随着这个剧烈倾斜的地轴来回摆动
you're stuck with this radical tilting of the axis back and forth,
从而气候会发生从未有过的剧烈变化
and therefore radical climate changes that don't happen today.
地球变成了非常怪异的世界
Earth becomes a very strange world,
人类要拼命去适应和挺过去
as mankind struggles to adapt and survive.
如果我们进入那种不稳定状况
If we go to a situation where we don't have that stabilization,
那些极小的变化都会变得非常的大
those very small changes become very, very big.
我们会进入到的状况
We may go to a situation
冰会持久地覆盖热带
where the ice becomes stable over the tropics.
设想一下 南极有丛林
Imagine jungles and forests in Antarctica
非洲中部有冰盖和冰川
and ice sheets and glaciers in central Africa.
倾斜会在几十万年的时间范围内发生变化
The tilt would vary on time scales of a few hundred thousand years.
那就是冰河降临地球的时期
These are time scales of ice ages coming upon the Earth.
我们知道影响会有多大
We know how much of an impact that had.
人类有过艰难的时期去适应这些变化
Humanity had a hard time adjusting to those changes
在我们走出上一个冰河时期时
as we came out of the last Ice Age.
很难预测究竟人类的结局如何
It's very difficult to predict exactly what would happen to humans,
因为我们没有把握我们能否很快去适应
because we're not sure how rapidly we're able to adapt
剧烈改变的环境
to radically changing environments.
如果我们的月球一去不复返了
And if our Moon disappeared permanently,
海里和岸上的生命会有彻底的改变
life in the sea and on the shore would be drastically transformed.
鲨鱼将丧失猎捕威力
Sharks would lose their hunting prowess,
无法追逐在月光下簇拥在它们头上的鱼群
unable to track the schools of fish swarming above them in the moonlight.
螃蟹 通常在退潮时交尾
Crabs, used to mating at extreme low tides,
会在月相消失后迷失方向
become disoriented at the loss of lunar phases.
在满月涨潮时产卵的银汉鱼
Grunion that lay their eggs during a high tide in full moon
则遭遇到繁殖的破坏
suffer reproductive disruption.
甚至原始的水生植物也会受到影响
Even primitive aquatic plant life would be affected.
许多物种会在海面上过夜
Many species will spend their evenings on the surface,
与月光互动
interacting with moonlight.
月亮升起 海藻也升起
The Moon comes up as the algae are moving up,
紧随其后的是所有以海藻为食的生物
and they're followed by all of the organisms
以及以它们为食的生物
that eat the algae and the organisms that eat them,
因而整个海洋生态是靠光调节的
so the whole ecology of the ocean is tuned to light.
所有这些生物通通被搞乱了
All of these organisms will be completely disrupted.
它们的生态已不起作用
None of their ecology will work,
因为它们将失去平常的传感信号
because they won't have the usual sensing signals.
万众将遭受到粮食短缺
Millions of people would suffer from food shortages,
沿海经济将随着全球性的海洋生物的毁灭
and coastal economies would be devastated
而遭灭顶之灾
by the worldwide crash in marine life populations.
我将它比作是我们突然一朝醒来
I would liken it to one of us suddenly waking up one morning
发现我们变成了瞎子 聋子
and discovering we were blind or deaf.
那将是一派混乱的事情
That would be a chaotic thing.
一颗没有月球的地球是一颗随波逐流的行星
An Earth without the Moon is a rudderless planet,
强调的就是这块大石头对维系生命在这里
highlighting just how critical this big rock is
是多么的关键
to sustaining life here.
我们太阳系里有150多颗卫星
There are over 150 moons in our solar system,
但是地球的月球确实与众不同
but Earth's Moon is truly unique.
我们的月球一点都不像太阳系里的其它卫星
Our Moon is unlike any of the other moons in the solar system.
它相比地球个头庞大
It is huge compared to Earth.
它约是地球大小的四分之一
It's about a quarter of the size of Earth,
是你在其他卫星所见不到的
and you don't see that in any of the other planets.
因为月球相对地球来说很大
Because the Moon is so big relative to the Earth,
仿佛我们就是在一个双星系里
it's as if we are really in a double-planet system.
有一个粗略的方法来思考月球稳定
There's a crude way to think about the effect of the Moon
地球这根轴倾斜的作用的
stabilizing this axial tilt of the Earth.
你是否注意到走钢丝人手持这根长杆
If you notice tightrope walkers will carry this long pole
那会给他们更多的稳定性
and that gives them more stability,
因为质量在杆子的两头
because there's mass out there on the end of the pole,
这样就不易掉下钢丝
and it's harder to fall off the line.
同样的情况 质量隔上一段距离
So it's that same kind of thing that the mass at a distance
可以影响到系统的稳定性
can affect the stability of the system.
不过月球并不是一直就在我们身边
But the Moon has not always been by our side.
地球早期有过一段时期
There was a time early in Earth's history
当时并没有月球
when there was no Moon,
一段时期里 我们的星球是个奇怪的地方每天8个小时
a period when our planet was a strange place with eight-hour days
熔化的大地 生命无法忍受
and a molten landscape too harsh for life,
接着遭遇了其历史上最猛烈的撞击
and then suffered the most violent collision in its history.
难以想象 但确实有过一段时间
It's hard to imagine, but there was a time
我们的地球没有月球
when our Earth did not have a Moon.
我们的星球形成于45亿年前
Our planet was formed 4 1/2 billion years ago
积聚并融合了我们不稳定的太阳系的
by accumulating and fusing large amounts of debris
早期阶段的大量碎片
in the early stages of our volatile solar system.
在那个早期阶段 我们无月的地球
During that early period, our moonless Earth
翻腾着可怕的熔岩
was a monstrous stew of flowing lava,
熔化的岩石以及液态铁
molten rock, and liquid iron.
其大气层里充满了地球深处喷出的二氧化碳
Its atmosphere was filled with carbon dioxide belched from the bowels of the Earth,
稠密厚重 不适宜生存
thick, heavy, and uninhabitable for life.
星球上光秃秃一片
There was almost nothing on the planet.
那是一个讨厌的地方
This was a nasty place to be.
很多东西正在凝固
Lots of things were condensing.
那是一个充满敌意的地方 哪怕对岩石化学
It was an extremely hostile place, even to rock chemistry.
岩石被熔化了
So the rocks were melted.
一切都一团糟
Everything was a mess.
我们最初的地球 没有自己的月球
Our original Earth, without its Moon,
是一个难以辨认的世界
was an unrecognizable world.
早期地球是一个炙热的地方
The early Earth was a really hot place.
事实上 地球的那个时期叫做冥古代
In fact, that era of the Earth is called the Hadean,
就像是冥府地狱一般 因为温度实在是高
like Hades, because, well  because it was really hot.
有大量的火山活动
There was a tremendous amount of volcanism
有大量的撞击
and a lot of impacts coming in.
或许有大量的闪电
There was probably a lot of lightning
排气分别来自火山和蒸汽
and out-gassing both from the volcanoes and from steam.
我们早期的太阳系的稳定性也好不到哪里去
The stability of our early solar system was not much better.
它打造出一个巨大的气体 碎片 尘埃盘
It was created out of a huge disk of gas, debris, and dust
盘旋在新生太阳的周围
that swirled around the newly formed Sun.
我们的早期太阳系就好象是一场轮滑比赛
Our early solar system was kind of like a roller derby.
人人都朝着一个方向跑
Everybody was generally going in the same direction,
但是一派混乱
but there was a lot of chaos.
有大量的挤碰
There was a lot of clumping and accreting
物体被抛向内部
and things getting flung to the inside
越线到外面
and crossing lanes to the outside.
人们相互挤在一起 跌倒在角落里
People all spilling over each other, mashing up in the corner.
真是乱作一团
It was a real mess.
没有月球 我们只能猜测
Without the Moon, we can only guess
地球早期的倾角和旋转速度
at the Earth's early tilt and rotation rate.
可以通过那些横冲直撞在我们早期太阳系里
That would have been determined by the multiple glancing collisions
的小行星和原行星
from the innumerable asteroids and protoplanets
多重随意的碰撞来得到确定
that ricocheted throughout our early solar system.
如果你来平均一下太阳系
If you kind of average over the solar system
来看一下所有的行星和大的小行星
and look at all the planets and the big asteroids
做一个旋转速度的正态分布曲线
and make a bell curve of rotation speeds,
看上去好象典型的转速
it looks like the typical rotation speed
可能就是8个小时 就是那样
might be eight hours, something like that.
所以我们可以做出猜测 那有可能就是
So we could make a guess that that might have been
月球形成之前的旋转速度
the likely rotation speed before the Moon was formed.
接着 在无月地球开始成形的1000万年后
Then, about 10 million years after our moonless Earth began taking shape,
发生了一次巨大的撞击
there was a massive collision.
现在天文学家已普遍接受
Now widely accepted by astronomers,
大碰撞说称 一颗火星大小的行星
the Giant Impact Theory says that a Mars-sized planet
以时速2 5万英里以一个斜角撞上地球
collided at an oblique angle at 25,000 miles per hour with Earth.
撞击者把地球七成以上的熔岩地壳撞进了太空
The impactor blasted more than 70% of the Earth's molten crust into space.
一条巨大的旋臂
A giant whirling arm,
由50亿立方英里的炽热的岩石和轻金属构成
made up of 5 billion cubic miles of blazing rock and light metals,
被射入了围绕我们星球的轨道上
was launched into orbit around our planet.
大块的重力开始把较小粒子拉向自己
The gravity of the larger chunks began pulling smaller particles towards them.
一年时间里 就凝结成了我们的月球
Within one year, it coalesced into our Moon.
唯一从地球上炸出去的材料
The only materials that were blown out from the Earth
是地壳岩石材料
were the crustal rocky material.
那就是月球的成分
And that's what the Moon's made out of.
事实上 如果你去到太阳系里任何一个地方
In fact, if you go to any other place in the solar system,
比如 火星
for example, Mars,
或者你看一下来自小行星带里的陨石
or you look at meteorites that come from the asteroid belt,
都含有一定比例的不同类型的氧气
there are certain ratios of the different types of oxygen.
太阳系里其他地方的那种比例
That ratio in other parts of the solar system
完全不同于我们在地球上所看到的
is very different than what we see in the Earth.
现在我们飞往月球
Now we fly to the Moon,
拿到月球岩石 将其带回来
we get the Moon rocks, we bring them back.
它们具有与地球上完全一样的氧同位素比例
They have exactly the same oxygen-isotope ratio as the Earth.
因此 材料出自地球
So that material came out of the Earth,
符合这个碰撞说的概念
and that fits this idea of an impact theory.
大碰撞所释放的能量
The energy released in the giant collision
等于6万亿个原子弹的当量
equaled a force of six trillion atomic bombs.
也就是目前地球人口60亿人
That's a thousand atom bombs for every person
每人1000个原子弹
in Earth's current population of six billion people.
打击地球的撞击行星
The impactor planet that hit Earth
被认为是形成于我们太阳系里的一个区域
was thought to have formed in an area of our solar system
叫做拉格朗日点
called the Lagrangian points.
那是地球前后分别60度的区域
These are regions 60 degrees either ahead of or behind the Earth,
然而是在距离太阳相近的位置上
but at a similar distance from the Sun.
碎片可以逗留在拉格朗日点上
Debris can stay fixed in the Lagrangian points
数千万年
for tens of millions of years,
被牢牢控制在日地之间的引力中
locked between the gravitational influence of the Sun and Earth.
但是最终 有东西将撞击者击出了它固定的轨道
But, eventually, something knocked the impactor off its fixed course.
那东西就是木星
That something was Jupiter.
每次木星在其轨道上经过我们时
Every time Jupiter passed by us in its orbit,
都会给这颗撞击行星施加一点小拉扯
it would be giving a little tug to this impactor planet.
每次小拉扯都不会很大
And each little tug wouldn't be very big.
不过你不妨想一想 举个例子
But if you think about, for example,
有一辆车被陷在沟渠里或陷在雪堆里
having a car that's stuck in a ditch or stuck in a snow bank,
你又是如何将车弄出雪堆的呢？
how do you get that car out of the snow bank?
对 你的办法就是来回推动车子
Well, the way you do it is you rock the car.
你推它一点点 它就回来一点点
You push it a little bit, it comes back,
推它越多一点 它就回来越远一点
push a little bit more, it comes back a little farther,
这样 随着雪堆的一点点推开
and this way, with a bunch of little pushes,
你最终释放了它
you eventually free it,
那正是木星对这颗撞击行星所干的
and that's exactly what Jupiter did to this impactor planet.
一旦它脱离了拉格朗日点
And once it gets away from the Lagrange point,
它就不安分了 劫数已定
it's no longer stable, and it's doomed.
它注定要撞上地球了
It's eventually going to collide with Earth.
经历了大灾变后
After the giant cataclysm,
喷射碎片的旋臂内部
the inner part of the whirling arm of ejected debris
形成了一个大块头 含有来自撞击者铁核的材料
forms a clump that consists of materials from the impactor's iron core.
那个大块头重新撞上地球
That heavier clump recollides with Earth
被吸纳进了我们星球的核心
and is absorbed into our planet's center.
大撞击确实是地球有史以来所发生的最大的事情
The giant impact was really the biggest thing that ever happened to Earth.
我们现在有了一个核心再加半个
What we have now is a core and a half.
那就使得我们的星球的密度
That makes our planet denser
和我们的重力更大更强于要是没有撞击
and our gravity stronger than it would be otherwise.
更大的熔核所需的冷却时间要长过
The larger molten core takes longer to cool
地球原始核心的冷却时间
than the Earth's original core would have.
热量源源不断地推高
Heat is constantly pushed up and through
并透过薄薄的地壳 创造出裂缝
the thin crust of the Earth, creating fissures.
或许就是这个更大的核心
It's possible that this larger core
帮助打造了持续的板块构造系统
helped create the sustained plate tectonic system
形成了我们的陆地
that formed our continents,
我们太阳系里的一个独特的行星特征
a unique planetary feature in our solar system.
作为例子 火星要小许多
As an example, Mars was much smaller.
它冷却地较快 所以它就没有地壳板块
It cooled much quicker, and so it has no crustal plates.
最为关键的是 撞击将地球撞到了
Most critically, the collision knocks the Earth
其目前的地轴倾角23 5度
onto its current axial tilt of 23 1/2 degrees
并将其转速从8小时加速到了5个小时
and speeds up its rotation from eight hours to just five hours.
不到一年时间 月球形成在距离地球约1 4万英里处
Within a year, the Moon forms roughly 14,000 miles away from Earth,
距离之近 大大超过了它目前的23 4万英里的距离
significantly closer than its current distance of 234,000 miles.
你会看到这个巨大的月球高挂空中
You've got this immense Moon in the sky,
是目前月球的15倍
15 times as big as the present Moon.
所以想想这玩意缓缓升起
So think about this thing rising and rising and rising
直到它占去了很大的一块夜空
until it fills up a pretty big chunk of that evening sky,
可以想象到它是彤红的 因为熔岩布满了
and imagine it being red because it's full of this molten lava
它的表面
around the surface.
想象它笼罩在你的头顶上
And imagine that looming over your head.
真是难以想象
It's mind-boggling.
早期月球对地球的引力
The early Moon's gravitational pull on Earth
大约要比现在强200倍
is roughly 200 times stronger than today
因为它的距离要近好多
because of its much closer distance.
尽管尚未出现海洋
Though no oceans exist yet,
但是月球的潮汐力要强上3400倍
the lunar tidal forces are 3,400 times more powerful.
它们抬起和落下巨大的熔岩地壳
They lift and drop large crusts of molten rock
超过半英里之高 一天两回
to more than half a mile high twice a day.
我们早期地轴的倾斜稳定得益于月球的形成
Our early planet's axial tilt stabilizes due to the Moon's formation,
其质量充当了一个锚具
and its mass acts as an anchor.
但是地球的旋转开始放慢
But the Earth's spin begins slowing,
因为月球的引力创造了一个潮汐隆起
because the Moon's gravitation creates a tidal bulge
围绕着我们星球的中部
around our planet's mid-section,
对地球自转产生了阻力
causing a drag on the Earth's rotation.
把地球看作是这个绿色的气球 这个是月球
Let the Earth be this green balloon, and here's the Moon.
如果地球没有自转
If the Earth weren't rotating,
潮汐隆起就会直接对准月球
the tidal bulge would point directly toward the Moon.
然而地球转动相当的快
But the Earth is rotating pretty quickly,
因此事实上 潮汐隆起会有一点点
so, in fact, the tidal bulge tends to be a little bit ahead
对准月球的趋势
of the direction toward the Moon.
这意味着月球的引力
That means the Moon's gravity
把地球的隆起拉回了一点点
is pulling back on the Earth's bulge a little bit,
稍稍减缓了它的自转
retarding its rotation ever so slightly.
但是地球上的潮汐隆起
But the tidal bulge on Earth
也会对月球有一个反作用力
also has a reactive force on the Moon.
这个潮汐隆起会拽着月球沿着轨道往前跑
This tidal bulge pulls the Moon ahead in its orbit.
它不断地试图拖着月球跑得更快
It's constantly trying to tug the Moon faster,
但是月球不想在自己的轨道上跑得更快
but the Moon doesn't want to go faster in its orbit.
结果却是
Instead what happens,
你不妨设想投掷一个弹弓 飞速地旋转它
if you imagine throwing a slingshot and swinging it faster,
它就会飞出去
it wants to go out.
那就是月球的情形
And that's what the Moon does.
它向外跑出去 因为它在轨道上被拖得越来越快了
It goes outward because it's being tugged faster in its orbit.
所以日积月累
So gradually over the years,
月球跑得越来越远了
the Moon is moving farther and farther out.
两个伙伴之间复杂的引力舞蹈
The complex gravitational dance between the two partners
现在正将月球推离地球
is now pushing the Moon away from Earth
速度是每年1 5英寸
at a rate of 1.5 inches per year.
经过了数十亿年
Over billions of years,
月球的后退已经减缓了地球的自转
the Moon's recession has slowed the Earth's rotation
从昼夜5小时到如今的昼夜24小时
from 5-hour days to our 24-hour day today.
这个地球自转受到月球影响的整个概念
The whole idea of this rotation of the Earth
有点像是你看
being influenced by the Moon is a little bit like what you see
花样滑冰运动员在旋转
when a figure skater is spinning
她收拢手臂旋转时 旋转加快
and when she pulls her arms in close and spins, she spins faster,
她舒展手臂就会慢下来
and she throws her arms out to slow down.
这就是物理学上所说的角动量
And this is all what the physicist would call angular momentum.
但是这也是月球往外跑的同样的道理
But it's the same idea as the Moon moved out.
有点像把手臂展开
It's kinda like throwing those arms out,
放慢了整个系统的旋转
and that slows down the rotation in the whole system.
但是要是大撞击未发生又将怎样呢？
But what if the giant impact had never happened?
地球的变化的急剧将远超过
The changes to Earth would be even more drastic
如果月球现在突然消失
than if the Moon now suddenly disappeared.
现在 我们是否会认可一个从来就没有过月球的地球
Today, would we recognize an Earth that never had a Moon,
会有人类存在吗？
and would humans even exist?
如果月球瞬间消失
If the Moon disappeared instantly,
地球所经受的变化可能会有海啸
Earth would undergo changes like possible tsunamis,
洋流的改变 海洋生物的灭绝
a shift in ocean currents, sea life extinctions,
最终大规模的气候波动
and eventual massive climate swings.
但要是月球从未出现过
But if the Moon had never existed,
地球将会是现在谁都认不出来的
Earth would be unrecognizable to anyone today.
没有月球 地球生命或将全然不同
Without the Moon, life on Earth would probably look quite different.
尤其是 人类将可能永远不会问世
In particular, humans might well never have come into existence.
在45亿年前无月的地球形成的1 5亿年后
About 150 million years after a moonless Earth forms 4.5 billion years ago,
它走出了炽热的熔化阶段 开始冷却
it moves out of its hot, molten phase and begins cooling.
昼夜只有8小时长
The day is only about eight hours long.
如果我们处于8小时的自转周期里
If we had an eight-hour rotation period,
我们就会有4小时白昼 4小时夜晚
we'd have four hours of daylight, four hours of night,
夜晚将漆黑一团 如果我们没有月球的话
and nights would be totally black if we don't have a Moon.
一旦冷却了 我们的星球将温暖到足以保留住水
Once cooled, our planet is temperate enough to retain water.
地核泄漏的热量
Heat escaping from Earth's core
将蒸汽和二氧化碳赶出地表
drives steam and carbon dioxide beyond the surface,
逐步形成了稠密的大气层
creating a thick atmosphere.
经过了一段时间 N多N多年后
Over a period of time, many, many, many, many years,
整个大气层就会塌缩回来
all that atmosphere would have kind of collapsed back out,
于是 随着它的冷却
and then, as it cooled,
海洋就诞生于疾风暴雨中
the oceans would have formed in torrential rainstorms.
冰态小行星持续不断地猛击地球
Icy asteroids continually pummel the planet,
带来了又一个大水源
bringing in another large source of water.
较小较冷的熔核 是没有可能板块构造的
With a smaller, cooler molten core, there are probably no plate tectonics,
因而 也就没有大山和巨大的海洋盆地的
and therefore, no large mountains and huge ocean basins.
水很快就就会覆盖星球大部分较为单调的地表
Water soon covers most of the planet's more uniform crust.
我们当然会看到比现在高的海平面
We certainly would have a higher sea level than we have today,
陆地很少
less continental area,
那是个别样的世界
and that would be a different world.
我们的蓝色星球更加蔚蓝
Our blue marble would be even bluer.
讽刺的是 尽管是那个水
Ironically, even with all that water,
早期无月的地球也会有一些不大的潮汐
the early moonless Earth would have smaller tides.
只是受制于太阳的引力
Determined only by the gravitation of the Sun,
它们只有我们现在潮汐的三分之一的规模
they would be just 1/3 the size of our current tides.
潮涨潮落之间的范围
The range between high and low tide
全年保持不变
would remain constant throughout the year
会发生在每天的同一时刻
and would occur at exactly the same time each day.
那意味着潮间带一直很窄
That means the intertidal regions would have been narrower,
几乎肯定会导致生命很少有变化
probably leading to less diversification of life
甚至会阻碍生命从海洋到陆地的进程
and perhaps even impeding the progress of life from the oceans to the land,
因为就是在潮间带里
because it's in the intertidal regions
生物才得以进化为能够同时生存在水陆之中
where creatures had to develop the ability to survive both in the water and on land.
由于昼夜8个小时 - 就4个小时有光线
With an eight-hour day-- just four hours of light
接着就是4小时的漆黑一团 -
followed by four hours of moonless black--
早期地球的自转快于今天3倍
the early Earth spins three times faster than today.
狂风怒吼 是因为地球快速旋转的空气动力学
The winds howl, due to the aerodynamics of Earth's quicker rotation.
木星 就是一例 是一颗飞速旋转的巨大行星
Jupiter, for example, is a giant planet that spins very rapidly.
它具有10小时的自转周期
It has a 10-hour spin period,
其大气层上部狂风肆孽
and it's got ferocious winds in its upper atmosphere,
时速数百英里
hundreds of miles an hour,
大红斑那样的惊人的风暴
and incredible storms like the Great Red Spot,
已存在了几个世纪
which has been around for centuries.
地球或许比现在旋转得更快
Now, Earth probably would be spinning more rapidly than it is now,
通常会引起强风
and that would generally lead to stronger winds
更加猛烈的飓风和其它风暴
and more violent hurricanes and other storms.
早期地球快速旋转导致了另一个重大的副作用
Early Earth's fast spin results in another important side effect.
地核的旋转
The rotation of Earth's core,
尤其是地核的熔化部分
particularly the molten part of the core,
据信就是它产生了我们的磁场
is believed to be what generates our magnetic field.
因而如果地球旋转快了三倍
And so if the Earth rotates three times faster,
磁场也会强上三倍
the magnetic field is three times stronger.
增强的磁场覆盖无月的地球
The enhanced magnetic field over the moonless Earth
更加有效地将高能太阳耀斑粒子偏转到
more effectively deflects high-energy solar flare particles
地球的两极
towards the Earth's poles,
产生出更大 更为壮观的极光
resulting in larger, more spectacular auroras.
但是通过阻挡太阳耀斑
But by blocking the solar flares,
就不会有太多的辐射来攻击大气层底部的生命
not as much radiation zaps life in the lower atmosphere,
减少了驱动进化的突变
decreasing mutations that drive evolution.
强磁场
A stronger magnetic field
可能会放慢地球生命进化的步伐
might have slowed the rate at which life evolved on Earth.
没有月球
Without the Moon,
发展中的地球会遭遇到剧烈的气候波动
the developing Earth suffers intense climate volatility.
历经许多纪 每纪都持续了数百万年
Over many periods, each lasting several million years,
地轴被太阳和其他行星推来拉去
the Earth's axis is pulled and pushed by the Sun and other planets.
没有月球的稳定作用
Without the stabilizing influence of the Moon,
环境将会类似于火星的遭遇
conditions would have paralleled what happened to Mars.
我们在过去15到20年里认识到
What we've learned in the last 15 or 20 years
火星有一个不稳定的星轴 因为它没有大卫星
is that Mars has a very unstable axis because it has no big moon.
我们观察火星时 实际上可以看到
And when we look at Mars, we can actually see
火星表面的地质地貌
on the surface of Mars geological features
形成于完全不同的气候条件下
that formed under very different climate regimes
当时极轴倾覆了
when the polar axis was tilted over.
火星上 我们其实看到了这些地貌
On Mars, we actually see these features,
就像是干涸的河道以及冰川沉积
like the dry river channels and glacial deposits
其他地貌 冰靠近赤道
and other features, ice close to the equator,
所以大认识就是
and so the big realization was
噢 对 气候一直在改变着火星
oh, yeah, the climate has been changing on Mars,
这就解释了我们所看到的较早期的地貌
and this explains that we're seeing older features.
和红色行星一样
Like the Red Planet,
无月地球的地轴也会疯狂倾斜
a moonless Earth's axis would tilt wildly,
把我们的星球搞得颠三倒四的
turning our planet topsy-turvy.
我们的地轴 在数百万年的时期里
Our axis, over a period of millions of years,
会乱七八糟地晃动
would wobble chaotically.
它时而垂直
It would sometimes be vertical.
时而接近水平
It would sometimes be close to horizontal.
它垂直时
When it's vertical,
整个地球就像是热带伊甸园
then the whole Earth might be kind of a tropical paradise.
它水平时 你实际上会看到
When it's horizontal, you could actually have
两极指向太阳
the poles pointing towards the Sun
极地实际上就逐步有了热带丛林
and the poles actually getting jungles.
所以你会看到地球气候的巨大变化
So you would see very big changes in Earth's climate
成为了地轴混乱摆动的结果
as a result of this chaotic wandering of Earth's axis,
这将给生命繁荣带来更大的困难
and this would make it more difficult for life to flourish,
因为它要去不断去适应各种环境 -
because it would constantly have to adapt to different conditions--
冰河时期到酷热时期
to ice ages and to extremely hot ages.
那么如果我们从来没有过月球
So what would life on Earth look like today
像现在这样的地球生命又会怎样呢？
if we had never had a Moon?
短昼夜 疾风 其他变化
Short days, high winds, and other changes
会产生出一个奇特的世界 生物
could produce a freakish world, with creatures
看上去就像是从科幻小说里走出来的
that look like they're straight out of science fiction.
月球形成于数十亿年前
The Moon was formed billions of years ago
当时一颗行星大小的小行星撞上了地球
when a planet-sized asteroid crashed into Earth.
然而要是那个剧烈碰撞从未发生过呢？
But what if that violent collision never happened?
如果月球从未出现来稳定我们的星球
If the Moon never came along to stabilize our planet,
地球将是一个化外之地
Earth would be an alien place.
早期地球的旋转很快
The spin of early Earth was very fast,
4个小时白昼 接着就是4个小时的黑暗
with about four hours of daylight, followed by four hours of darkness.
在数十亿年里 太阳引力及潮汐摩擦
Over billions of years, the Sun's gravity and tidal friction
会将每天8小时延长到12小时
would lengthen that 8-hour day to 12 hours.
但这依然是目前地球旋转速度的两倍
But this is still twice as fast as the current Earth spins,
就会产生出一些极端天气
which makes for some extreme weather,
包括毁灭性的风暴和疾风
including devastating storms and high winds.
如果月球没有形成
If the Moon hadn't formed,
你肯定会有一个面目全非的地球环境
you'd certainly get a wildly different environment on the Earth.
由于快速旋转的地球 你就有了更多的射流
With a faster-turning Earth, you get more jet streams,
你或许就有更多的涡流 甚至更大的风暴
you get more turbulence probably, maybe bigger storms,
更多的电闪雷鸣 是空气流动中的
more lightning because of the friction
不同云团的摩擦所致
of the different masses of air moving.
在某些地方 风速可以达到时速100或200英里
In some places, the winds could reach 100 or 200 miles an hour.
还有更强的飓风
There would also be stronger hurricanes,
地球会有更大的海浪拍打海岸线
and Earth would have larger waves battering the coastlines.
没有月亮的稳定作用
And without the Moon's stabilizing effect,
快速旋转的地球会来回摆动
the rapidly spinning Earth tilts back and forth.
在数十万年里
Over hundreds of thousands of years,
我们的星球遭受了不断变化的气候的蹂躏
our planet suffers the ravages of ever-shifting climate
那是地轴倾角的无规则变化造成的
because of the erratic changes in axial tilt,
各个地区一会儿酷热难当
as different regions are blasted by heat,
一会儿冰天雪地 反复无常
then covered by ice again and again.
没有了月球
And without the Moon,
还有另一层地轴的不稳定性
there is another layer of axial instability.
尽管现在的地球是月球来稳定的
Even though today's Earth is stabilized by the Moon,
但还是存在地球自转的摆动
there is still a wobble to the Earth's rotation,
叫做岁差
known as precession.
地球的倾角为23 5度
Earth's tilt is 23 1/2 degrees,
但是在一个2 6万年的周期里
but over a period of 26,000 years,
它会走过这样的锥形变差
it goes through conical variations like this.
如果月球从未面世
And if the Moon had never formed,
这种摆动将会更加难以预测
this wobbling would be much more unpredictable.
要是我们没有月球
If we didn't have the Moon,
地球的进动将会慢很多
the Earth would precess much more slowly,
这是源于地轴倾角的混乱变化
and this is one cause for chaotic variations in the axial tilt.
地球的慢进动
A slower precession of the Earth
会导致地球自转轴的更不稳定
would lead to a much more unstable axis of rotation for the Earth.
没有月球 现在的地轴
Without the Moon, Earth's axis today
就会像越转越慢的陀螺一样
would be like the slower spinning top,
边进动 边旋转 晃动在更大的圆锥面上
precessing, gyrating, and wobbling in ever larger conical circles.
眼下 2 6万年 很稳定的区间
Right now, 26,000 years, a very stable zone,
你看到它越走越慢 或许4万
you get It going slower, so it's maybe 40,000,
或许5万 或许6万年
maybe 50,000, maybe 60,000,
你会遭遇到一个混乱的时段 那时一切都出毛病了
then you hit the chaotic range, and then everything goes wrong.
由于愈加恶劣 反复无常的气候
With the more forbidding and shifting climate,
无月地球的进化摆动在
evolution on a moonless Earth varies
突发性适应和剧烈的灭绝之间
between bursts of adaptation and violent extinction.
怪诞的生命形式如雨后春笋
Bizarre life forms mushroom.
植物物种很脆弱 因为它们不具备机动性
Plant species are vulnerable, as they don't have the mobility
走在快速的气候变化的前头
to stay ahead of speedy climate change.
复杂的生命形式 如人类
And complex life forms like humans
或许根本就没什么机会
probably wouldn't stand a chance at all.
气候变化将是极端和快速的
The variations in climate would be extreme and rather rapid,
或许会让复杂生物的进化难以为继
and it would probably make it difficult for complex creatures to evolve,
因为大多数复杂生物的进化不可能非常快速地
because most complex creatures can't evolve very quickly
在它们的环境中进行变化
to changes in their environment.
相反 原始有机体会占上风并坚持下去
Instead, primitive organisms would predominate and endure.
细菌不仅能够更快地适应
Bacterial life is able not only to adapt more quickly,
而且还能承受更为极端的环境
but also to withstand more extreme environments.
我们看到细菌在南极和格陵兰的冰芯深处
We see bacteria under the deep ice cores of the Antarctic or Greenland,
我们看到细菌
and we see bacteria
生活在黄石公园沸腾的水穴里
that live in steaming, boiling pots in Yellowstone.
如果复杂生命得以进化 它看上去绝对别样
If complex life were to evolve, it would look very different,
因为短昼夜 疾风
due to short days, high winds,
以及无月地球的其它特征
and other features of a moonless Earth.
要比现在严酷的多
It would be much more hostile than it is now.
你会看到那些风 那些声音
You would see that all of these winds and all of the noise
那些云彩
and all of the clouds.
生命从水里走向陆地将异常艰难
Moving from water to life on land would be very tough,
我们可能会看到较短的寿命
and we might see shorter life spans,
因为事情发展太快了
because things are going on faster.
白天 时间有限
During the day, there will be a limited time
去新陈代谢 去获取能量 去做事情
to metabolize and gain energy and do things.
生物体必须要更机灵一点才行
Organisms would have to be a little more clever.
进化将偏好短小粗壮的动植物
Evolution would favor short, stout creatures
它们可以抵挡猛烈的飓风
and plant life that could withstand ferocious hurricanes.
丛林将不会存在 因为它们需要风障才得以茂盛
Jungles wouldn't exist since they need wind barriers to flourish.
可能不会有任何生物
And there probably wouldn't be any creatures
在树枝上荡来荡去
swinging from branch to branch,
那是因为粗矮植物和疾风的缘故
due to stubbier plant life and high winds.
我预计生物一般都不会长得很高
I would expect the creatures generally wouldn't be as tall,
因为它们很难保持直立
because they'd have a harder time holding themselves up.
根系很浅的树木不会长得很高
And trees with shallow root systems wouldn't become very tall.
棕榈树 举个例子 或许不会存活
Palm trees, for example, probably wouldn't survive too well.
持续的强风会推动其它的适应
The constant gusts would push other adaptations.
风帆 你知道 很可能是膜
Sailing, you know, maybe membranes,
让你飞起来 跃上天空
that let you take off and leap through the air
没完没了的狂风环境
And the perpetual gale-like conditions
会打造出一个格外喧闹的行星
would create an exceptionally loud planet.
如果动物用声音来进行沟通
If animals made noises to communicate,
它们就必须完全区别于连续呼啸的风声
they'd have to be very different from the constant shrieking wind sounds.
使用的声音在波长上
The use of sound at wavelengths
不是背景噪音的声音
that are not the sound of the background noise.
如果你有感官能消除那个噪音
If you have a receptor that just zeros out that noise,
我们就能够像这样来说话并听个明白
we might be able to speak like this and be heard perfectly.
我们都会成为女高音的
We might all be sopranos
耳朵都调到另外的音调
and have ears tuned to a different pitch.
或更多的视觉提示可能会进化成
Or more visual cues might be developed
穿透音频超载
to cut through the audio overload.
生物可能会进化出额外的肢体
Creatures might develop extra limbs
不仅能挡风
to not only shield themselves from the wind,
而且还能利用附属肢体来进行沟通
but also use their appendages to communicate
就像水手使用旗语信号一样
like sailors using semaphore signals.
或许说话能力不会发展起来
Perhaps speech would not develop,
因此也许其它沟通方式
so maybe other forms of communication,
会不会是颜色变化
whether color changes,
表情变化 手语 谁知道呢？
expression changes, hand languages, who knows?
即使在现在 有许多地球生物 如萤火虫
Even today, many of Earth's beings, such as fireflies,
鱿鱼
squids,
磷虾 水母
krill, and jellyfish,
沟通就是靠改变它们身体的颜色
communicate by changing their body colors.
因为在黑夜里
Because of the dark nights,
生物也可能进化出增强的视觉和感官系统
creatures might also develop enhanced vision and sensory systems
类似于夜视镜
similar to the night vision goggles
以及军用红外显示器
and infrared displays used by the military.
有趣之事
The interesting possibility
在于生命有可能进化出感官
is that life might be able to develop sensors
非常有效 它们实际上可以感觉到星光
that were so good that they could actually sense starlight,
那是很了不起的东西
and this would be something colossal.
它看上去貌似危险狂野的世界
It looks and sounds like a rough and too tough world,
不适合人类居住
unfit for human habitation.
幸运的是 月球形成后
Luckily, when the Moon formed,
它创造了人类发展繁荣的环境
it created the conditions for people to develop and prosper.
但是我们的月球也正在逐年远离地球
But our Moon is also moving farther away from Earth every year.
那是否意味着会有地球将来那么一天
Does that mean there will be another time
失去月球呢？
in Earth's future without the Moon?
45亿年前
4 1/2 billion years ago,
年轻的地球是一个炼狱 不适合生命
the young Earth was a hellish molten place, unfit for life.
那么一个火星般大小的天体在地球形成后不久
So then how did a violent collision by an object the size of Mars
猛烈地撞上地球又是如何
soon after the Earth's formation
创造环境适合复杂生命 包括今天的我们的呢？
create the conditions for the complex life we're part of today?
打击地球的天体把我们星球敲打到目前的倾角
The body blow to Earth knocked our planet to its current tilt
月球的形成使之保持了下来
and the formation of the Moon kept it there.
月球的质量放在那边
The mass of the Moon out there,
它的作用就是防止其他行星的拖拉
what it's done is it's prevented the tugs of the other planets
从而造成地球倾角的过度变化
from causing the Earth's tilt to change too much.
由此它对我们的气候真正发挥了稳定作用
So it provided a real stabilizing effect on our climate because of that.
碰撞也创造了力量的连锁反应
The collision also created a chain reaction of forces
奠定了生命的舞台
that set the stage for life.
两颗星星的铁核合并后
When the iron cores of the two planets combined,
就产生了新地球更大的地核
it created a larger core for the new Earth.
碰撞也敲掉了地球的大部分地壳
The collision also knocked off much of the Earth's crust.
这个兼并 有大量的热量
This combination, with large amounts of heat
从巨大的地核中透过薄薄的地壳被推了出来
pushing up from a giant core through a thin crust,
可能创造了持续的板块构造的条件
likely created the conditions for sustained plate tectonics.
这些板块的运动形成了山脉和盆地
The movement of these plates formed mountain ranges and deep basins,
产生的火山活动
and the resulting volcanic activity
喷出的气体形成了我们的大气层
spewed out the gases that created our atmosphere.
水最终安家在了盆地里 形成了海洋
Water eventually settled in the basins, creating oceans,
把陆地留在了高处
leaving continents of land above.
然而生命还要有一段艰苦的岁月才能
But life still had a tough time getting started
诞生于早期的地球
in the early days of Earth.
对于地球和月球出现后的头5亿年来说
For the first half billion years of the Earth's and the Moon's existence,
它们遭遇到了尚在完成太阳系形成的
they were bombarded by debris that was still finishing up
碎片的狂轰滥炸
the formation of the solar system.
因此即使有原始生命 微生物和细菌
So even if primitive life, microbes and bacteria,
形成于最早的几亿年里
had formed in the first few hundred million years,
它们也可能轻而易举就被那些撞入地球的
they might easily have been wiped out
庞然大物所消灭
by these giant things crashing into Earth.
现在 我们有证据证明生命可追溯到38亿年前
Now, we have evidence for life dating back to 3.8 billion years ago.
那是重轰炸期结束后不久的事
That's shortly after the end of the Era of Heavy Bombardment.
那时 由于地月之间的潮汐摩擦
By then, due to tidal friction between the Earth and Moon,
月球已稍稍远离了地球
the Moon had moved slightly farther away from Earth,
地球的自转已减慢到了大约一天10小时
and Earth's rotation had slowed to roughly a 10-hour day.
但是由于月球依然比今天近许多
But since the Moon was still much closer than today,
地球早期海洋的潮汐是滔天海浪
the tides in Earth's early oceans were humongous.
潮汐侵入内陆又倒回大海
The tides went way inland and poured back out to sea.
一天两次 你会有大海湾 海水灌入
Twice a day, you'd get a big gulf of water in,
它一旦回流 就把大量的矿物质和土壤
and when it drained back out, it carried a lot of minerals and soils
以及地壳的其它成分随之带回了大海
and other parts of the Earth's crust back out to sea with it.
因而 就有了这种对陆地的持续侵蚀和冲刷
So there was this constant erosion and scrubbing of the land.
无疑 一个独特的环境
Certainly a unique environment
有可能正好适合生命的发展
that might have been just right for life to develop.
涨潮 落潮间的区域
The area between high and low tide,
叫做潮间带 面积巨大
known as the intertidal region, was enormous.
涨潮会冲入数百英里的内陆
High tides would rush hundreds of miles inland,
然后数小时后退潮
then back out a few hours later.
退潮时 分子链开始形成于
During the low tides, molecular strands began forming
望不到头的潮池中的一些
in some of the endless miles of tide pools.
水蒸发后会发生什么？
What happens when water evaporates?
水分子消失了 别的都留下了
The H2O molecules go away, and everything else is left.
这样潮池中的有机污泥
So the organic sludge in the pool
随着水的蒸发变得越来越浓缩
gets more and more concentrated as the water evaporates,
这就是生命诞生于这些小潮池的概念
so this was the idea that life formed in these little pools.
约5 7亿年前
Around 570 million years ago,
差不多是大碰撞后39亿年
almost 3.9 billion years after the giant impact,
地球上的海洋生命开始走向陆地
Earth's ocean life begins moving onto land,
逐步诞生出复杂物种
giving birth to complex species.
潮间带区域越大
The bigger the intertidal regions,
导致的生命多样性就越大
the greater the resulting diversity of life,
因为你可以有物种生活在这些环境中
because you can have species that live in these environments
有时暴露在阳光下
that are sometimes exposed to the Sun
有时在水下
and sometimes underwater.
经过了数十亿年
Over billions of years,
我们地球似乎达到了完美的平衡
our Earth seems to have reached a perfect equilibrium
已能承担起丰富多彩
that has allowed for the evolution of a diverse,
错综复杂 脆弱的生态系统的进化
intricate, and fragile ecosystem.
有些气候太单调了
There are some climates that are too uniform,
没有季节变化等等 不会导致生命
no seasonal changes and so on, and don't lead to life,
因为没有环境压力
because there's no environmental stress.
而另一方面 气候太多变
And, on the other hand, climates that are too variable,
季节一直变个不停
where the seasons are changing all the time,
你每百万年就遭遇一颗小行星的打击
you're getting hit by an asteroid every million years,
那样的行星可能会设法形成生命
planets like that would probably try to form life,
但是它们难以走下去
but they couldn't get it going,
因为事情变化太快了
because things would change too fast.
因此或许会有一个环境 刚好处在中间
So maybe there's a situation that's just right in the middle,
或许地月系统就在那范围的某个地方
and maybe the Earth-Moon system is somewhere in that range,
它促进了 不光是原始生命的形成
which has fostered, not only formation of primitive life,
而且生命还进化到了我们这样的人类
but the evolution of that life into folks like us.
尽管我们的月球稳定着局面
But though our Moon stabilizes things,
但它在不断地退离我们 每年1 5英寸
it continues to recede from us at a rate of an inch and a half inch per year
同时也在减慢我们的自转
while it slows our spin.
科学家估计我们每10万年 昼夜增加2秒钟
Scientists estimate that we're adding 2 seconds to our day every 100,000 years.
距今10亿年后
A billion years from now,
我们每天会有26小时 而不是24小时
our days might last 26 hours, rather than 24 hours,
那太好了 如果你像我这样 拖拖拉拉的话
which is great if you're a procrastinator like me.
你可以一直用上更多的时间了
You could always use more time.
那么会对产生地球生命的这种独特的
So what will happen to the unique Earth-Moon partnership
地月伙伴关系产生什么后果呢？
that made life on Earth possible?
月球最终会不会慢慢离去
Will the Moon eventually just drift away
摆脱地球的引力影响呢？
out of Earth's gravitational influence?
速度会很慢很慢 不会有很大的影响
The rate will be so slow that it won't be a very big effect,
长长的时间里不会有太大的变化
and long periods of time will pass without much change,
时间会长到我们有时间让我们的太阳
so long that we will have had time for our Sun
耗尽燃料成为一颗红巨星
to run out of fuel and become a red giant.
到了那时 地球行将毁灭
At that time, the Earth will be destroyed,
所以月球也将同时报销
and so will the Moon at the same time.
我们会一起受到煎熬
We'll all get baked together.
或许令人欣慰的是 距今50亿年后
So maybe it's comforting to know that 5 billion years from now,
在地球临终之日 我们并不孤独
on the day the Earth faces its end, we won't be alone.
我们天上的锚具会呆在那里
Our anchor in the sky will be there